So, HTTP in C++, how hard could it be?
Turns out not very hard with CPP HTTP
lib. So, this is a C++ 11 single file
header only crossplatform HTTP/HTTPS
library. We've done heaps of networking
related stuff on this channel with C++,
but we haven't actually looked at HTTP.
For those of you who don't know what
that is and how that's different to the
networking we've been doing, this might
not be the video for you. I don't know.
Should I explain all the different
networking things? No, probably not.
Anyway, what you're looking at here is
HTTP. The way that we requested this
website from some kind of server
somewhere on the internet, it got
delivered here. We can render it and
display it. That happens using something
called HTTP. It's just a protocol that
we use to transfer data over a network.
It's different than what we've been
doing so far, which is a little bit more
raw with TCP and UDP. This is a lot
higher level in that it lets us create
an actual server and then serve some
kind of content. And then on the client
side, we would create a client with some
sort of HTTP address like this and then
use different methods such as get or
post to actually request data. Which
means that if you're not making some
sort of multiplayer game or you're not
streaming data constantly, you just want
to be able to, I don't know, have a
database on a server and then read that
from C++ for whatever reason, you would
most likely use something like HTTP. You
would request something from the server.
The server would do all the processing
and then it would serve you something.
Now, this library over here, CPP HTTP
lib, is the simplest thing I've used in
my experience. I mean, it's a C++ 11
compatible single file header only
cross-platform library. Literally, all
you have to do is grab this http.h file
and just include it. Include it in a CBP
file and you're ready to go. So today
we're going to take a look at how to use
this and we're going to look at the full
picture including how to actually surf
some data from our server so that we can
then request and use it in C++. And to
make things a little bit easier and to
have an actual UI instead of just a
command line tool, we're going to be
using Walnut. I'll have a link in
description below to both Walnut and
HTTP lib. Okay, so over here in Walnut,
we have a really really simple example.
Most of this is actually just the
example code that comes from the dev
branch of walnut in the example app. I
have literally set up like the most
simple HTTP example I could think of.
First and foremost, we have to include
this HTTP lib file. So, here it is. This
is this is the file. All I did was just
grab like this raw file and just save
it. And then I'm just including it.
That's it. That's how easy it is to use
this library. And then what I'm doing is
in the constructor of this example
layer, I'm actually creating a client
with an IP address. This is the IP
address of a hosting a server that I set
up for this. We'll have a look at that
in a minute. And then what I'm doing is
requesting this API page that gives me
some kind of result. This is the status
of the result. So usually you'd expect
it to be 200. These are just HTTP status
codes. I'm just printing that so that we
have some kind of idea as to what's
going on. And then the body of the
result is going to be a string which I'm
storing inside this data string and then
later rendering. Again, really really
simple example. We're going through the
constructor first. We're grabbing the
data and then we're reading from it. So
there's really no need for threads or
asynchronous programming in this case.
Doing this on the main thread like this
will probably increase your startup time
slightly, but it's okay. We'll have a
look at a more complicated example later
in this video. So if we give this a run,
once it opens, we have our data window
with secret information. So this is the
string that we're actually retrieving
from the server. So what exactly is a
server doing? Let's have a look at that.
A server provided of course by
Hostinger, the sponsor of this video. So
Hostinger is by far my favorite web host
on the internet because they have really
really high quality servers at really
affordable prices and they actually have
a Black Friday sale on at the moment
which reduces their prices even more. So
if you go to hosting.com/cho you can
have a look at all of their servers. The
great thing about hosting is that they
use AMD epic processes and NVME SSDs.
You can see that every plan comes with
all of these things and that's really
really important for performance. They
also use KVM servers which just means
that your server is running
independently. Of course, you get full
route access to do whatever you need on
your server and that together with their
excellent TOS protection and firewall
just means that you're getting an
excellent deal. So, if we pick this KVM2
plan here for example over here at
checkout, make sure that you use coupon
code churn to get an even bigger
discount. Once you have got a server,
it's time to set it up. Now, the setup
process is super quick and simple. All
you have to do is select a location for
your server. They show you all the
latencies here which makes it really
easy to select something close to you or
you can pick something closer to your
users. There's a huge range of operating
systems to choose from. I usually go
with Abuntu. And finally, just set a
root password and you're done. Hostinger
will now set up your server and this
usually takes only a couple minutes. And
that's it. You're done. You can now
session to your server and do whatever
you like. As I mentioned, Hostinger have
an amazing Black Friday sale that is on
at the moment. So go to hosting.com/cho.
link will be in description below and
don't forget to use coupon code churno
at checkout for an additional discount.
Huge thank you to Hostinger for
sponsoring this video. Okay, so once we
SSH into our server, I'm actually using
the remote SSH plugin over here in
Visual Studio Code. Now, I've talked
about this before, but this is by far my
favorite way to like work with servers
because it just opens up an environment
right here in VS Code with a terminal,
with an explorer, with everything on
that hosting a server. I just needed to
make sure that I installed engine X.
That's my preferred web server that I
like to use. So, I just did that and
that's it. I'm now running EngineX,
which by default on a fresh install just
sets up var www. html as the directory
for your website. At least that's the
default website that it sets up for you
at the root of our server. If we just go
to etc and then engine x, we have sites
available and sites enabled. So, if we
look at sites available default, that's
the default configuration that engine x
comes from. And then you can see that
the root here is var www html. that
directory is the root of this particular
site that we are serving. These are all
of the possible index pages, etc.
Anyway, this isn't a tutorial on how to
set up like a website using EngineX, but
for those of you who might not know much
about this, hopefully this gives you
some insight as to how it works. So, if
we switch on over into that HTML
directory, then we have of course the
default index page. If we navigate to
our servers IP address just in a web
browser like this, then this is what
we'll see. We'll see this page being
rendered here. Now, from here, I just
made a new file. I called it API just
with no extension and I put some text in
it. Secret information. That is all you
need. So now you should be able to see
how we just go to this IP address and
then / API and that's the file. We're
basically just requesting that file by
using get and the HTTP server in this
case engine X is serving us that file.
Now we can change that. Let's just
change this to say like new information
from Cherno. We'll save that file and
then we'll just run our program again.
And then check it out. We have new
information from Cherno. So yes, as I
mentioned, really, really simple
example. However, if you're just getting
started with this kind of stuff and you
don't know how it works and you just
don't need all that extra complexity,
this is the simple case. This is just
what we're doing. And with HTTP lib, you
can see it's really easy to just grab
some data from a server. Now, from here,
the possibilities are endless. You could
have like some PHP code. Hopefully not.
You could have some code running here
like server side even. You could be
using JavaScript. It might be requesting
some information from an actual
database, building up like a whole like
JSON kind of response for you with all
the information you need. You can really
do anything you want with this. Now
you've made that connection between
server and client. Now let's take a look
at a slightly more complicated example.
We're going to have a look at the
weather. So I did a little bit of
googling and I found this free weather
API openmeo.com.
You can see it's got an example over
here as to how we can request some data
from the API. And then the response is
just in JSON. Now I have adapted this to
show the weather of Melbourne. That's
where I live. I just typed in Melbourne
latl long. Here it is. I put that over
here into the HTTP get request. And
that's it. It just gives us the current
temperature over here. 19.7° C. Getting
this into our C++ application is no
different than what we just did with the
exception of probably wanting to pass
this JSON. For the JSON paring, I'm
using this library over here. I'll have
it linked in the description below as
well. But then weather is also something
that we probably want to keep updating.
So if the app is running, I don't really
want to just fetch the weather, the
temperature once at the beginning and
then just that's it. I want to keep
requesting it because I want that
information to be up to date. So that's
also something that this slightly more
complicated example shows as well. So if
we just hit F5 and take a look then you
can see that we have ta the weather over
here it's 19.7° awesome. However the
difference is that every minute this
will actually update. So how does that
work? If we have a look at how it's
actually using that HTTP lib is
basically the same thing. We just have
our client that we set up with this
website over here and then we request
something using get. As you can see it's
just this URL. Of course, once again,
we're printing the status, but then
we're using that JSON library to
actually pass it. And then we're
grabbing the current temperature because
that is what we need to do to get this
double here. So, this is actually a
double. All the extra complexity, all
the extra code around this is just to
make this operation asynchronous. The
thing is, we're running our UI rendering
every frame and we don't want any kind
of network activity to interfere with
that because requesting something like
this from a server takes time. You can
also see that this literally has to
wait. It's a blocking operation to wait
until we actually get that data back.
It's not like we're setting up a call
back and it will notify us later when
it's available. No, like we just call
get and that's it. Here's the result
over here. So, it has to happen
synchronously, which is fine as long as
we have a separate thread that we set up
over here. So, we're creating a new
thread. It's this request thread over
here that runs this function. And then
it will just execute this code over and
over again, he says as he forgot the
while loop. So, this is what I meant to
write. That's funny. Now realistically
you want this to terminate if the
application like is requested to be
closed and all of that but this is just
a simple example. Let's just ignore
that. So we have this loop that will run
this code over and over again. However,
you can see that it will sleep for 1
minute. So it will run it like every
minute but again on a separate thread.
So this is kind of running concurrently
just sleeping mostly while we are
continually updating our UI every frame.
But then how do we get the data? How do
we get the actual temperature from this
thread to this thread? So many ways, so
many different ways to do that. This is
probably my favorite way in this case
for this scenario to do that. The
simplest way would probably be to just
create like a mutex around the string
that is like the weather info in this
case. That's what we're displaying in
the UI. That's what the temperature is.
You could lock the mutex, set the
temperature from this thread, then
unlock the mutex, and then on the UI
thread, lock the mutex, render, unlock
the mutex, or at least lock the mutex,
copy the data to a local string, unlock
the mutex, and then later render with
that local string. However, that
requires locking a mutx every single
frame, even though like we barely update
this data like once per minute. You know
how many frames we render in a minute?
If this is running at VSync on my
monitor, which is 144 hertz, that's a
lot of frames. That's a lot of needless
locking unlocking mutexes. It just it
doesn't feel very good. So instead, we
double buffer this. We have two
different strings and then an index into
which one of the two strings we're
basically working with. This index is
also atomic to make sure that we're not
reading and writing to it at the same
time. So then all we have to do is in
the common case when we're just trying
to render it, we just grab like whatever
the current index is and we use that to
actually access this weather info array.
But then when it's time to update the
data, we grab that current index and we
increment it. We write into the other
index. So we could be reading at the
same time, but we're reading from a
different index because we haven't
atomically written it yet. We're writing
to one index, for example, index number
one. We're reading from index number
zero. And then finally, when that write
has completed, we're going to store the
new index, which means that next time we
load this, it'll be our new index, and
we are reading and rendering the new
updated data. Anyway, this is just a
brief look into this kind of stuff. I
didn't really plan this to be like a
multi-threading tutorial or, you know,
too much kind of multi-threading
related. It's mostly about the HTTP of
course, but this is just the kind of
stuff you need to do when you are
dealing with networking. You need to
make sure that a lot of your stuff is
running asynchronously if it is
repeatedly requested like this. I mean,
honestly, even in the other example, I
would also make that asynchronous. It's
just I was trying to be really simple
and not involve threads at all. If you
guys are interested in seeing more
networking or multi-threaded related
content, let me know in the comment
section below. Currently in the first
example we looked at in this video we
were just using engine X as our HTTP
server. However, HTTP lib can also
create servers. So that would be
something that I would love to explore
in a future video. And also SSL we have
not touched anything to do with HTTPS
because that involves roping in more
libraries. Again trying to keep things
simple but that is probably something
that I would take a more serious look at
in a more serious context. Hope you guys
enjoyed this video. If you did, please
don't forget to hit the like button.
Definitely check out hosting.com/churn.
They have some amazing Black Friday
deals on at the moment. It's honestly
the best time of year to pick up a
server. Thank you all for watching. I'll
see you next time. Goodbye.